<section>
    <title>Sets</title>
    <p>Modern mathematics makes heavy use of <em>sets</em>. A set is an unordered collection of
        distinct objects. We won’t try and pin it down more than this—our intuition about
        collections of objects will suffice<fn> When you pursue more rigorous math, you rely on
        definitions to get yourself out of philosophical jams. For instance, with our definition of
        set, consider “the set of all sets that don’t contain themselves”. Such a set cannot exist!
        This is called <em>Russel’s Paradox</em><idx>
                <h>Russel’s Paradox</h>
            </idx>, and shows that if we start talking about
        sets of sets, we may need more than intuition.</fn>. We write a set with curly-braces <m>\{</m>
        and <m>\}</m> and list the objects inside. For instance</p>
    <p>
        <me>\Set{1,2,3}.</me>
    </p>
    <p>This would be read aloud as “the set containing the elements <m>1</m>, <m>2</m>, and <m>3</m>”.
        Things in a set are called <em>elements</em><idx>
            <h>Set!element of</h>
        </idx>, and the symbol <m>\in</m><idx>
            <h>symbols</h>
            <h>
                <m>\in</m>
            </h>
        </idx> is used to specify that something is an
        element of a set. In contrast, <m>\notin</m><idx>
            <h>symbols</h>
            <h>
                <m>\notin</m>
            </h>
        </idx> is used to specify something is not an
        element of a set. For example,</p>
    <p>
        <me>3\in\Set{1,2,3}\qquad 4\notin\Set{1,2,3}.</me>
    </p>
    <p>Sets can contain mixtures of objects, including other sets. For example,</p>
    <p>
        <me>\Set{1,2,a,\Set{-70,\infty}, x}</me>
    </p>
    <p>is a perfectly valid set.</p>
    <p>It is tradition to use capital letters to name sets. So we might say <m>A=\{6,7,12\}</m> or <m>
        X=\{7\}</m>. However there are some special sets which already have names/symbols associated
        with them. The <em>empty set</em><idx>
            <h>Set!empty</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Set!empty</h>
        </idx> is the set containing no elements and is written <m>
        \emptyset</m><idx>
            <h>symbols</h>
            <h>
                <m>\emptyset</m>
            </h>
        </idx> or <m>\Set{}</m>. Note that <m>
        \Set{\emptyset}</m> is <em>not</em> the empty set—it is the set containing the empty set! It
        is also traditional to call elements of a set <em>points</em><idx>
            <h>Point!of a set</h>
        </idx> regardless of whether you consider them
        “point-like”.</p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Operations on Sets</title>
    <p>If the set <m>A</m> contains all the elements that the set <m>B</m> does, we call <m>B</m> a <em>
        subset</em> of <m>A</m>. Conversely, we call <m>A</m> a <em>superset</em> of <m>B</m>.</p>
    <definition xml:id="SubsetSuperset">
        <title>Subset &#x26; Superset</title>
        <statement>
            <p>The set <m>B</m> is a <em>subset</em><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Subset</h>
                </idx> of the set <m>A</m>, written <m>B\subseteq A</m><idx>
                    <h>symbols</h>
                    <h>
                        <m>\subseteq</m>
                    </h>
                </idx>, if for all <m>b\in
                B</m> we also have <m>b\in A</m>. In this case, <m>A</m> is called a <em>superset</em><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Superset</h>
                </idx> of <m>B</m>.<fn> Some mathematicians use
                the symbol <m>\subset</m> instead of <m>\subseteq</m>.</fn></p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>Some simple examples are <m>\Set{1,2,3}\subseteq \Set{1,2,3,4}</m> and <m>
        \Set{1,2,3}\subseteq\Set{1,2,3}</m>. There’s something funny about that last example,
        though. Those two sets are not only subsets/supersets of each other, they’re <em>equal</em>.
        As surprising as it seems, we actually need to define what it means for two sets to be
        equal.</p>
    <definition xml:id="SetEquality">
        <title>Set Equality</title>
        <statement>
            <p>The sets <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are <em>equal</em><idx>
                    <h>Set!equality</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Set!equality</h>
                </idx>, written <m>A=B</m>, if <m>A\subseteq
                B</m> and <m>B\subseteq A</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>Having a definition of equality to lean on will help us when we need to prove things about
        sets.</p>
    <example>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be the set of numbers that can be expressed as <m>2n</m> for some whole
                number <m>n</m>, and let <m>B</m> be the set of numbers that can be expressed as <m>
                m+1</m> where <m>m</m> is an odd whole number. We will show <m>A=B</m>.</p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>First, let us show <m>A\subseteq B</m>. If <m>x\in A</m>, then <m>x=2n</m> for some
                whole number <m>n</m>. Therefore</p>
            <p>
                <me>x=2n=2(n-1)+1+1=m+1</me>
            </p>
            <p>where <m>m=2(n-1)+1</m> is, by definition, an odd number. Thus <m>x\in B</m>, which
                proves <m>A\subseteq B</m>.</p>
            <p>Now we will show <m>B\subseteq A</m>. Let <m>x\in B</m>. By definition, <m>x=m+1</m>
                for some odd <m>m</m>. By the definition of oddness, <m>m=2k+1</m> for some whole
                number <m>k</m>. Thus</p>
            <p>
                <md>
                    <mrow>x=m+1&#x26;=(2k+1)+1=2k+2</mrow>
                    <mrow>&#x26;=2(k+1)=2n,</mrow>
                </md>
            </p>
            <p>where <m>n=k+1</m>, and so <m>x\in A</m>. Since <m>A\subseteq B</m> and <m>B\subseteq
                A</m>, by definition <m>A=B</m>.</p>
        </solution>
    </example>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Set-builder Notation</title>
    <p>Specifying sets by listing all their elements can be a hassle, and if there are an infinite
        number of elements, it’s impossible! Fortunately, <em>set-builder notation</em><idx>
            <h>Set-builder notation</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Set-builder notation</h>
        </idx> solves these problems. If <m>X</m> is a set,
        we can define a subset</p>
    <p>
        <me>Y= \Set{a\in X\given\text{some rule involving }a},</me>
    </p>
    <p>which is read “<m>Y</m> is the set of <m>a</m> in <m>X</m> <em>such that</em> some rule
        involving <m>a</m> is true.” If <m>X</m> is intuitive, we may omit it and simply write <m>Y=\Set{a\given\text{some
        rule involving }a}</m><fn> If you want to get technical, to make this notation unambiguous,
        you define a <em>universe of discourse</em>. That is, a set <m>\mathcal{U}</m> containing
        every object you might want to talk about. Then <m>\Set{a\given\text{some rule involving }a}</m>
        is short for <m>\Set{a\in\mathcal{U}\given\text{some rule involving }a}</m>.</fn>. You may
        equivalently use “<m>|</m>” instead of “<m>:</m>”, writing <m>Y=\{a\,|\,\text{some rule
        involving }a\}</m>.</p>
    <p>There are also some common operations we can do with two sets.</p>
    <definition xml:id="UnionsIntersections">
        <title>Unions &#x26; Intersections</title>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>X</m> and <m>Y</m> be sets. The <em>union</em><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Set!union</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>Set!union</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>symbols</h>
                    <h>
                        <m>\cup</m>
                    </h>
                </idx> of <m>X</m> and <m>
                Y</m> and the <em>intersection</em><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Set!intersection</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>Set!intersection</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>symbols</h>
                    <h>
                        <m>\cap</m>
                    </h>
                </idx> of <m>X</m> and <m>
                Y</m> are defined as follows.</p>
            <p>
                <dl>
                    <li>
                        <title>(union)</title>
                        <p><m>X\cup Y = \Set{ a \given a\in X\text{ or }a\in Y}</m>.</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <title>(intersection)</title>
                        <p><m>X\cap Y = \Set{ a \given a\in X\text{ and }a\in Y}</m>.</p>
                    </li>
                </dl>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>For example, if <m>A=\Set{1,2,3}</m> and <m>B=\Set{-1,0,1,2}</m>, then <m>A\cap B=\Set{1,2}</m>
        and <m>A\cup B= \Set{-1,0,1,2,3}</m>. Set unions and intersections are <em>associative</em>,
        which means it doesn’t matter how you apply parentheses to an expression involving just
        unions or just intersections. For example <m>(A\cup B)\cup C=A\cup(B\cup C)</m>, which means
        we can give an unambiguous meaning to an expression like <m>A\cup B\cup C</m> (just put the
        parentheses wherever you like). But watch out, <m>(A\cup B)\cap C</m> means something
        different than <m>A\cup(B\cap C)</m>!</p>
    <p></p>
    <p>Some common sets have special notation:</p>
    <p>
        <md>
            <mrow>\emptyset&#x26;= \Set{}\text{, the empty set}</mrow>
            <mrow> \N\index[symbols]{$\N$}&#x26;= \Set{0,1,2,3,\ldots}=\Set{\text{natural numbers}}</mrow>
            <mrow> \Z\index[symbols]{$\Z$}&#x26;= \Set{\ldots,
                -3,-2,-1,0,1,2,3,\ldots}=\Set{\text{integers}}</mrow>
            <mrow> \Q\index[symbols]{$\Q$}&#x26;= \Set{\text{rational numbers}}</mrow>
            <mrow> \R\index[symbols]{$\R$}&#x26;= \Set{\text{real numbers}}</mrow>
            <mrow> \R^{n}\index[symbols]{$\R^{n}$}&#x26;= \Set{\text{vectors in $n$-dimensional
                Euclidean space}}</mrow>
            <mrow></mrow>
        </md>
    </p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Vectors &#x26; Scalars</title>
    <p>A <em>scalar</em><idx>
            <h>Scalar</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Scalar</h>
        </idx> number (also referred to as a <em>scalar</em> or just an
        ordinary <em>number</em>) models a relationship between quantities. For example, a recipe
        might call for <em>six</em> times as much flour as sugar. In contrast, a <em>vector</em><idx>
            <h>Vector</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Vector</h>
        </idx> models a relationship between points. For example, the store
        might be <em>2km East and 4km North</em> from your house. In this way, a vector may be
        thought of as a <em>displacement</em> with a <em>direction</em><idx>
            <h>Vector!direction of</h>
        </idx> and a <em>magnitude</em><idx>
            <h>Vector!magnitude of</h>
        </idx><fn> Though in this book we will treat vectors
        as geometric objects relating to Euclidean space, they are much more general. For instance,
        someone’s internet browsing habits could be described by a vector—the topics they find most
        interesting might be the “direction” and the amount of time they browse might be the
        “magnitude.” </fn>.</p>
    <p>Given points <m>P=(1,1)</m> and <m>Q=(3,2)</m>, we specify the <em>displacement</em><idx>
            <h>Displacement</h>
        </idx> from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m> as a vector <m>
        \overrightarrow{PQ}</m> whose magnitude is <m>\sqrt{5}</m> (as given by the Pythagorean
        theorem) and whose direction is specified by a directed line segment from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m>
        .</p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Vector Notation</title>
    <p>There are many ways to represent vector quantities in writing. If we have two points, <m>P</m>
        and <m>Q</m>, we write <m>\overrightarrow{PQ}</m> to represent the vector from <m>P</m> to <m>
        Q</m>. Absent points, a bold-faced letter (like <b class="textbf">a</b>) or an arrow over a
        letter (like <m>\vec a</m>) are the most common vector notations. In this text, we will use <m>\vec
        a</m> to represent a vector. The notation <m>\norm{\vec a}</m><idx>
            <h>symbols</h>
            <h>
                <m>\norm{\:\cdot\:}</m>
            </h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>Vector!magnitude of</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>Vector!norm of</h>
        </idx> represents the magnitude of the vector <m>\vec a</m>,
        which is sometimes called the <em>norm</em> or <em>length</em> of <m>\vec a</m>.</p>
    <p>Graphically, we may represent vectors as directed line segments (a line segment with an arrow
        at one end), however we must take care to distinguish between the picture we draw and the
        “true” vector. For example, directed line segments always <em>start</em> somewhere, but a
        vector models a displacement and has no sense of “origin”.</p>
    <p>Consider the following: for the points <m>A=(1,1)</m>, <m>B=(3,2)</m>, <m>X=(1,0)</m>, and <m>
        Y=(3,1)</m>, define the vectors <m>\vec a = \overrightarrow{AB}</m> and <m>\vec
        x=\overrightarrow{XY}</m>.</p>
    <p>Are these the same or different vectors? As directed line segments, they are different
        because they are at different locations in space. However, both <m>\vec a</m> and <m>\vec x</m>
        have the same magnitude and direction. Thus, <m>\vec a=\vec x</m> despite the fact that <m>A\neq
        X</m><fn> Some theories use <em>rooted vectors</em><idx>
                <h>Vector!rooted</h>
            </idx> instead of vectors as the fundamental object
        of study. A rooted vector represents a magnitude, direction, <em>and</em> a starting point.
        And, as rooted vectors, <m>\vec a\neq \vec x</m> (from the example above). But for us,
        vectors will always be unrooted, even though our graphical representations of vectors might
        appear rooted. </fn>.</p>
    <remark>
        <title>Takeaway</title>
        <p>A vector is not the same as a line segment and a vector by itself has no “origin”.</p>
    </remark>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Vectors and Points</title>
    <p>The distinction between vectors and points is sometimes nebulous because the two are so
        closely related. A <em>point</em><idx>
            <h>Point!in Euclidean Space</h>
        </idx> in Euclidean space specifies an absolute
        position whereas a vector specifies a displacement (i.e., a magnitude and direction).
        However, given a point <m>P</m>, one associates <m>P</m> with the vector <m>\vec
        p=\overrightarrow{OP}</m>, where <m>O</m> is the origin. Similarly, we associate the vector <m>\vec
        v</m> with the point <m>V</m> so that <m>\overrightarrow{OV}=\vec v</m>. Thus, we have a way
        to unambiguously go back and forth between vectors and points<fn> Mathematically, we say
        there is an <em>isomorphism</em><idx>
                <h>Isomorphism</h>
            </idx> between vectors and points (once an origin is
        fixed, of course!).</fn>. As such, <em>we will treat vectors and points interchangeably</em>
        .</p>
    <remark>
        <title>Takeaway</title>
        <p>Vectors and points can and will be treated interchangeably.</p>
    </remark>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Vector Arithmetic</title>
    <p>Vectors provide a natural way to give directions. For example, suppose <m>\xhat</m> points
        one kilometer eastwards and <m>\yhat</m> points one kilometer northwards. Now, if you were
        standing at the origin and wanted to move to a location 3 kilometers east and 2 kilometers
        north, you might say: “Walk 3 times the length of <m>\xhat</m> in the <m>\xhat</m> direction
        and 2 times the length of <m>\yhat</m> in the <m>\yhat</m> direction.” Mathematically, we
        express this as</p>
    <p>
        <me>3\xhat+2\yhat.</me>
    </p>
    <p>Of course, we’ve incidentally described a new vector. Let <m>P</m> be the point at 3-east and
        2-north. Then</p>
    <p>
        <me>\overrightarrow{OP}=3\xhat+2\yhat.</me>
    </p>
    <p>If the vector <m>\vec r</m> points north but has a length of 10 kilometers, we have a similar
        formula:</p>
    <p>
        <me>\overrightarrow{OP}=3\xhat+\tfrac{1}{5}\vec r,</me>
    </p>
    <p>and we have the relationship <m>\vec r=10\yhat</m>. Our notation here is very suggestive.
        Indeed, if we could make sense of “<m>\alpha\vec v</m>” (scalar multiplication) and “<m>\vec
        v+\vec w</m>” (vector addition) for any scalar <m>\alpha</m> and any vectors <m>\vec v</m>
        and <m>\vec w</m>, we could do algebra with vectors.</p>
    <p>We will define scalar multiplication<idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Vector operations!scalar multiplication</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>Vector operations!scalar multiplication</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>Vector operations!addition</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>definitions</h>
            <h>Vector operations!addition</h>
        </idx> intuitively: For a vector <m>\vec v</m>
        and a scalar <m>\alpha>0</m>, the vector <m>\vec w=\alpha\vec v</m> is the vector pointing
        in the same direction as <m>\vec v</m> but with length scaled by <m>\alpha</m>. That is, <m>\norm{\vec
        w}=\alpha\norm{\vec v}</m>. Similarly, <m>-\vec v</m> is the vector of the same length as <m>\vec
        v</m> but pointing in the exact opposite direction.</p>
    <p>For two vectors <m>\vec u</m> and <m>\vec v</m>, the sum <m>\vec w=\vec u+\vec v</m>
        represents the displacement vector created by first displacing along <m>\vec u</m> and then
        displacing along <m>\vec v</m>.</p>
    <remark>
        <title>Takeaway</title>
        <p>You add vectors tip to tail and you scale vectors by changing their length.</p>
    </remark>
    <p>Now, there is one snag. What should <m>\vec v+(-\vec v)</m> be? Well, first we displace along <m>\vec
        v</m> and then we displace in the exact opposite direction by the same amount. So, we have
        gone nowhere. This corresponds to a displacement with zero magnitude. But, what direction
        did we displace? Here we make a philosophical stand.</p>
    <definition xml:id="ZeroVector">
        <title>Zero Vector</title>
        <statement>
            <p>The <em>zero vector</em><idx>
                    <h>Zero vector (<m>\vec 0</m>)</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Zero vector (<m>\vec 0</m>)</h>
                </idx>, notated as <m>\vec 0</m><idx>
                    <h>symbols</h>
                    <h>
                        <m>\vec 0</m>
                    </h>
                </idx>, is the vector
                with no magnitude.</p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>We will be pragmatic about the direction of the zero vector and say, <em>the zero vector does
        not have a well-defined direction</em><fn> In the mathematically precise definition of
        vector, the idea of “magnitude” and “direction” are dropped. Instead, a set of vectors is
        defined to be a set over which you can reasonably define addition and scalar multiplication. </fn>.
        That means sometimes we consider the zero vector to point in every direction and sometimes
        we consider it to point in no directions. It depends on our mood—but we must never talk
        about <em>the</em> direction of the zero vector, since it’s not defined.</p>
    <p>Formalizing, for vectors <m>\vec u</m>, <m>\vec v</m>, <m>\vec w</m>, and scalars <m>\alpha</m>
        and <m>\beta</m>, the following laws are always satisfied:</p>
    <p>
        <md>
            <mrow>(\vec u+\vec v)+\vec w&#x26;=\vec u+(\vec v+\vec w)\tag{Associativity}</mrow>
            <mrow> \vec u+\vec v&#x26;=\vec v+\vec u\tag{Commutativity}</mrow>
            <mrow> \alpha(\vec u+\vec v)&#x26;=\alpha\vec u+\alpha \vec v\tag{Distributivity}</mrow>
        </md>
    </p>
    <p><idx>
            <h>Vector operations!laws of</h>
        </idx> and</p>
    <p>
        <md>
            <mrow>(\alpha\beta)\vec v&#x26;=\alpha(\beta \vec v)\tag{Associativity II}</mrow>
            <mrow> (\alpha+\beta)\vec v&#x26;=\alpha\vec v+\beta \vec v\tag{Distributivity II}</mrow>
        </md>
    </p>
    <p>Indeed, if we intuitively think about vectors in flat (Euclidean) space, all of these
        properties are satisfied<fn> If we deviate from flat space, some of these rules are no
        longer respected. Consider moving 100 kilometers north then 100 kilometers east on a sphere.
        Is this the same as moving 100 kilometers east and then 100 kilometers north? </fn>. From
        now on, these properties of vector operations will be considered the <em>laws (or axioms) of
        vector arithmetic</em>.</p>
    <p>We group scalar multiplication and vector addition under one name: <em>linear combinations</em>
        .</p>
    <definition xml:id="LinearCombination">
        <title>Linear Combination</title>
        <statement>
            <p>A <em>linear combination</em><idx>
                    <h>Linear combination</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Linear combination</h>
                </idx> of the vectors <m>\vec
                v_{1},\vec v_{2},\ldots,\vec v_{n}</m> is a vector</p>
            <p>
                <me>\vec w = \alpha_{1}\vec v_{1}+\alpha_{2}\vec v_{2}+\cdots+\alpha_{n}\vec v_{n}.</me>
            </p>
            <p>The scalars <m>\alpha_{1},\alpha_{2},\ldots,\alpha_{n}</m> are called the <em>
                coefficients</em><idx>
                    <h>Linear combination!coefficient of</h>
                </idx><idx>
                    <h>definitions</h>
                    <h>Linear combination!coefficient of</h>
                </idx> of the linear
                combination.</p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Coordinates and the Standard Basis</title>
    <p>Consider the standard, flat, Euclidean plane (which is notated by <m>\R^{2}</m>). A
        coordinate system for <m>\R^{2}</m> is a way to assign a unique pair of numbers to every
        point in <m>\R^{2}</m>. Though there are infinitely many coordinate systems we could choose
        for the plane, there is one standard one: the <m>xy</m>-coordinate system depicted below
        (which you’re already familiar with).</p>
    <p>In conjunction with the standard coordinate system, there are also <em>standard basis vectors</em><idx>
            <h>Standard basis</h>
        </idx><idx>
            <h>Basis!standard basis</h>
        </idx>. The vector <m>\xhat</m> always points one
        unit in the direction of the positive <m>x</m>-axis and <m>\yhat</m> always points one unit
        in the direction of the positive <m>y</m>-axis.</p>
    <p>Using the standard basis, we can represent every point (or vector) in the plane as a linear
        combination. If the point <m>P</m> has <m>xy</m>-coordinates <m>(\alpha,\beta)</m>, then <m>
        \overrightarrow{OP}=\alpha\xhat+\beta\yhat</m>. Not only that, but this is the <em>only</em>
        way to represent the vector <m>\overrightarrow{OP}</m> as a linear combination of <m>\xhat</m>
        and <m>\yhat</m>.</p>
    <remark>
        <title>Takeaway</title>
        <p>Every vector in <m>\R^{2}</m> can be written uniquely as a linear combination of the
            standard basis vectors.</p>
    </remark>
    <p>For a vector <m>\vec w=\alpha\xhat+\beta\yhat</m>, we call the pair <m>(\alpha,\beta)</m> the <em>standard
        coordinates</em><idx>
            <h>Coordinates</h>
        </idx> of the vector <m>\vec w</m>. There are many equivalent
        notations used to represent a vector in coordinates.</p>
    <p>Coordinates and vectors go hand in hand, and we will often write</p>
    <p>
        <me>\vec v=\mat{\alpha\\\beta}</me>
    </p>
    <p>as a shorthand for “<m>\vec v=\alpha\xhat+\beta\yhat</m>”.</p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Solving Problems with Coordinates</title>
    <p>Coordinates allow for vector arithmetic to be carried out in a mechanical way. Suppose <m>\vec
        u=\mat{a\\b}</m> and <m>\vec v=\mat{x\\y}</m>. Then,</p>
    <p>
        <me>\vec u=\vec v\qquad\iff\qquad \mat{a\\b}=\mat{x\\y}\qquad\iff\qquad a=x\text{ and }b=y.</me>
    </p>
    <p>Further,</p>
    <p>
        <me>\vec u+\vec v=\mat{a\\b}+\mat{x\\y}=\mat{a+x\\b+y}\qquad\text{and}\qquad t\vec
            u=t\mat{a\\b}=\mat{ta\\tb}</me>
    </p>
    <p>for any scalar <m>t</m>.</p>
    <p>Using these rules, otherwise complicated questions about vectors can be reduced to simple
        algebra questions<fn> So simple, that computers are able to answer billions of such
        questions a second as you play your favorite video game!</fn>.</p>
    <example>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>\vec x=\xhat-\yhat</m>, <m>\vec y=3\xhat-\yhat</m>, and <m>\vec
                r=2\xhat+2\yhat</m>. Is <m>\vec r</m> a linear combination of <m>\vec x</m> and <m>\vec
                y</m>?</p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>By definition, <m>\vec r</m> is a linear combination of <m>\vec x</m> and <m>\vec y</m>
                if there exist scalars <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> such that</p>
            <p>
                <me>\vec r= a\vec x+b\vec y.</me>
            </p>
            <p>Rewriting everything in coordinates, we see this is equivalent to the equation</p>
            <p>
                <me>\mat{2\\2}=a\mat{1\\-1}+b\mat{3\\-1}= \mat{a+3b\\-a-b}.</me>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, we need to determine if the system of equations</p>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \left\{\begin{array}{crcrl}&#x26;a&#x26;+&#x26;3b&#x26;=2\\-&#x26;a&#x26;-&#x26;b&#x26;=2
                    \end{array}\right.</me>
            </p>
            <p>has a solution. After solving, we find <m>a=-4</m> and <m>b=2</m> is the only
                solution. Thus, <m>\vec r</m> is a linear combination of <m>\vec x</m> and <m>\vec y</m>.
                More specifically,</p>
            <p>
                <me>\vec r = -4\vec x+2\vec y.</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </example>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Higher Dimensions</title>
    <p>We coordinatize three dimensional space (notated by <m>\R^{3}</m>) by constructing <m>x</m>, <m>
        y</m>, and <m>z</m> axes. Again, <m>\R^{3}</m> has standard basis vectors <m>\xhat</m>, <m>
        \yhat</m>, and <m>\zhat</m> which each point one unit along the <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>
        axes, respectively.</p>
    <p>Since we live in three dimensional space, its study has a long history, and many notations
        for the standard basis of three dimensional space are in use. This text will use <m>\xhat</m>
        , <m>\yhat</m>, <m>\zhat</m>, but other common notations include:</p>
    <p>Beyond three dimensions, drawing pictures becomes hard, but we can still use vectors. We use <m>
        \R^{n}</m> to notate <m>n</m>-dimensional Euclidean space. The standard basis for <m>\R^{n}</m>
        is <m>\sbasis{1}</m>, <m>\sbasis{2}</m>, …, <m>\sbasis{n}</m>. Again, every vector in <m>
        \R^{n}</m> can be written uniquely as a linear combination of the standard basis, and a
        coordinate representation of a vector in <m>\R^{n}</m> is a list of <m>n</m> scalars.</p>
    <example>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>\vec x,\vec y\in\R^{3}</m> be given by <m>\vec x=2\xhat-\zhat</m> and <m>\vec
                y=6\yhat+3\zhat</m>. Compute <m>\vec z=\vec x+2\vec y</m>.</p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \vec z=\vec x+2\vec y=\quad\mat{2\\0\\-1}+2\mat{0\\6\\3}\quad
                    =\quad\mat{2\\0\\-1}+\mat{0\\12\\6}\quad=\quad\mat{2\\12\\5}\quad=2\xhat+12\yhat+5\zhat</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </example>
</section>